Last year,
العام الماضي
three of my family members were gruesomely murdered
ثلاثة من أفراد عائلتي تم قتلهم بفظاعة
in a hate crime.
في جريمة بدافع الكراهية
It goes without saying that it's really difficult
بلا شك، هذا موقع صعب
for me to be here today,
بالنسبة لي أن أكون هنا اليوم
but my brother Deah,
لكن أخي ضياء
his wife Yusor,
زوجته يُسر
and her sister Razan
وأختها رزان
don't give me much of a choice.
لم يعطوني الكثير من الخيارات
I'm hopeful that by the end of this talk you will make a choice,
أنا آمل أنه بنهاية كلامي اليوم أنتم ستختارون
and join me in standing up against hate.
وتشاركوني للوقوف ضد الكراهية
It's December 27, 2014:
27 ديسمبر 2014
the morning of my brother's wedding day.
صباح يوم زواج أخي
He asks me to come over and comb his hair
طلب مني القدوم ومساعدته في تمشيط شعره
in preparation for his wedding photo shoot.
تحضيرًا من أجل صور الزواج
A 23-year-old, six-foot-three basketball, particularly Steph Curry, fanatic --
بعمر 23 سنة وبطول 6 أقدام لاعب كرة سلة بالتحديد من المعجبين بـ(ستيف كيري)
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
An American kid in dental school ready to take on the world.
شاب أمريكي في كلية طب الأسنان مستعد لينطلق في الحياة
When Deah and Yusor have their first dance,
عندما رقص ضياء ويسر رقصتهم الاولي
I see the love in his eyes,
رأيت الحب في عينيه
her reciprocated joy,
ومبادلتها له الفرحة
and my emotions begin to overwhelm me.
ومشاعري بدأت تغمرني
I move to the back of the hall and burst into tears.
تحركت إلي آخر القاعة وانهمرت بالبكاء
And the second the song finishes playing,
وفي اللحظة التي تنتهي فيها الأغنية
he beelines towards me,
يتحرك نحوي
buries me into his arms
ويعانقني بين يديه
and rocks me back and forth.
ويهزني إلى الأمام والخلف
Even in that moment,
حتى في تلك اللحظة
when everything was so distracting,
عندما كان كل شيء مشوشًا
he was attuned to me.
كان هو متابعًا لي
He cups my face and says,
يضع يديه على وجهي ويقول
"Suzanne,
"سوزان،
I am who I am because of you.
أنا ما أنا عليه بسببك أنتِ
Thank you for everything.
شكرًا لكل شيء
I love you."
أنا أحبك"
About a month later, I'm back home in North Carolina for a short visit,
بعد شهر تقريبًا وفي أثناء عودتي لكارولينا الشمالية من أجل زيارة قصيرة
and on the last evening, I run upstairs to Deah's room,
في آخر ليلة صعدت لغرفة ضياء
eager to find out how he's feeling being a newly married man.
متحمسة لأعرف ما هو شعوره وهو رجل متزوج حديثًا
With a big boyish smile he says,
بابتسامة كبيرة قال لي
"I'm so happy. I love her. She's an amazing girl."
"أنا سعيد جدًا وأحبها. إنه امرأة مميزة"
And she is.
وهي كذلك
At just 21, she'd recently been accepted to join Deah
بعمر 21 تم قبولها حديثًا لتنضم لضياء
at UNC dental school.
في كلية طب الأسنان جامعة كارولينا الشمالية
She shared his love for basketball, and at her urging,
شاركتة حبه لكرة السلة، وبناءً على إلحاحها
they started their honeymoon off attending their favorite team of the NBA,
ذهبا في شهر العسل لحضور مباراة فريقهما المفضل في البطولة الوطنية
the LA Lakers.
فريق لوس انجليس ليكرس
I mean, check out that form.
انظروا إلى هذا
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I'll never forget that moment sitting there with him --
لن أنسى تلك اللحظة عندما كنت جالسة معه
how free he was in his happiness.
كيف كان سعيدًا وحرًا
My littler brother, a basketball-obsessed kid,
أخي الصغير المهووس بكرة السلة
had become and transformed into an accomplished young man.
تحول وأصبح رجلاً له إنجازات كثيرة
He was at the top of his dental school class,
كان في مقدمة زملائه في كلية طب الأسنان
and alongside Yusor and Razan,
ومع يسر ورزان
was involved in local and international community service projects
كان مشاركًا في خدمات المجتمع الخيرية دوليًا ومحليًا
dedicated to the homeless and refugees,
المقدمة للاجئين والمشردين
including a dental relief trip they were planning
بالإضافة لرحلة
for Syrian refugees in Turkey.
من أجل اللاجئين السوريين في تركيا
Razan, at just 19,
رزان بعمر 19
used her creativity as an architectural engineering student
استخدمت إبداعها كطالبة في الدراسة المعمارية
to serve those around her,
في خدمة الناس الذين حولها
making care packages for the local homeless,
تساعد في إنتاج مواد مساعدة للمشردين
among other projects.
من ضمن مشاريع أخرى
That is who they were.
هذا ما كانوا عليه
Standing there that night,
واقفين هناك في تلك اليلة
I take a deep breath and look at Deah and tell him,
أخذت نفسًا عميقًا ونظرت إلى ضياء وقلت له
"I have never been more proud of you than I am in this moment."
"لم أكن فخورة بك أبدًا أكثر من هذه اللحظة"
He pulls me into his tall frame,
شدني إلى قامته الطويلة
hugs me goodnight,
وحضنني
and I leave the next morning without waking him
وغادرت في الصباح التالي دون أن أيقظه
to go back to San Francisco.
لأعود إلى سان فرانسيسكو
That is the last time I ever hug him.
تلك كانت آخر مره حضنته فيها
Ten days later, I'm on call at San Francisco General Hospital
بعد عشرة أيام وأنا في مناوبة في مستشفى سان فرانسيسكو العام
when I receive a barrage of vague text messages expressing condolences.
بدأت في استقبال كمية من رسائل المواساة الغامضة
Confused, I call my father, who calmly intones,
كنت مشوشة، اتصلت بوالدي الذي تحدث معي بهدوء شديد
"There's been a shooting in Deah's neighborhood in Chapel Hill.
"لقد حدث إطلاق نار في حي ضياء في شابيل هيل
It's on lock-down. That's all we know."
والشرطة تحاصر المكان وهذا كل ما نعلم"
I hang up and quickly Google, "shooting in Chapel Hill."
أغلقت الهاتف وفتحت غوغل "إطلاق نار في شابيل هيل"
One hit comes up.
وظهرت معلومة
Quote:
أقتبس:
"Three people were shot in the back of the head
"ثلاث أشخاص أُطلقت النار عليهم في مؤخرة رؤوسهم
and confirmed dead on the scene."
و تم إعلان الوفاة في موقع الحادث."
Something in me just knows.
و شيء في داخلي علم.
I fling out of my chair and faint onto the gritty hospital floor,
أصبت بالإغماء ووقعت من كرسيّ في أرض المستشفى،
wailing.
وأنا أصرخ.
I take the first red-eye out of San Francisco,
ركبت في أقرب رحلة إلى سان فرانسيسكو
numb and disoriented.
مخدرة وشاردة الذهن.
I walk into my childhood home and faint into my parents' arms,
دخلت إلى منزل طفولتي ووقعت بين يدي والدي
sobbing.
أبكي بصوت عالٍ
I then run up to Deah's room as I did so many times before,
بعدها ذهبت إلى غرفة ضياء كما فعلت كثيرًا من قبل،
just looking for him,
أبحث عنه،
only to find a void that will never be filled.
فقط لأرى فراغه الذي لا يمكن أن يمتلئ مجددًا.
Investigation and autopsy reports eventually revealed
تم إعلان تقرير التحقيق والتشريح الجنائي
the sequence of events.
وتوضيح تسلسل الأحداث.
Deah had just gotten off the bus from class,
ضياء كان قد نزل من الحافلة عائدًا من جامعته،
Razan was visiting for dinner,
رزان كانت في زيارة لتناول الغداء،
already at home with Yusor.
وقد كانت في المنزل مع يسر.
As they began to eat, they heard a knock on the door.
ومجرد أن بدأوا بتناول الطعام سمعوا الباب يُطرق.
When Deah opened it,
وعندما فتح ضياء الباب،
their neighbor proceeded to fire multiple shots at him.
بدأ جارهم بإطلاق عدد طلقات عليه.
According to 911 calls,
وبناء على الهاتف الطارئ
the girls were heard screaming.
قد سمع صوت البنات يصرخن
The man turned towards the kitchen and fired a single shot into Yusor's hip,
تقدم الرجل نحو المطبخ وأطلق طلقة على ورك يسرى،
immobilizing her.
لكي يشل حركتها.
He then approached her from behind,
وبعدها وصل إليها من الخلف،
pressed the barrel of his gun against her head,
وثبّت رأس مسدسه في رأسها،
and with a single bullet, lacerated her midbrain.
وبطلقة واحدة اخترق دماغها.
He then turned towards Razan, who was screaming for her life,
وبعدها توجه لرزان التي كانت تصرخ
and, execution-style, with a single bullet
وبطريقة الإعدام ذاتها، بطلقه واحدة،
to the back of the head,
أطلق النار على رأسها من الخلف،
killed her.
وقتلها.
On his way out,
في طريقه إلى الخارج،
he shot Deah one last time -- a bullet in the mouth --
أطلق النار لآخر مرة في فم ضياء،
for a total of eight bullets:
ليكون قد أطلق ثماني طلقات عليه بالمجمل
two lodged in the head,
اثنتان في الرأس،
two in his chest
اثنتان في الصدر،
and the rest in his extremities.
والباقي في أطرافه.
Deah, Yusor and Razan were executed
تم إعدام ضياء ويسر ورزان
in a place that was meant to be safe: their home.
في مكان كان من المفترض أن يكون آمناً: منزلهم.
For months, this man had been harassing them:
لعدة أشهر هذا الرجل كان يزعجهم:
knocking on their door,
يدق على بابهم،
brandishing his gun on a couple of occasions.
يظهر ويلوح بمسدسه في عده مناسبات.
His Facebook was cluttered with anti-religion posts.
صفحته في الفيس بوك مليئة بمنشورات ضد الدين
Yusor felt particularly threatened by him.
شعرت يسر تحديدًا أنها مهددة من قبله.
As she was moving in,
وعندما كانت يسر تنتقل للسكن،
he told Yusor and her mom that he didn't like the way they looked.
قال لها ولأمها أنه لا يحب أشكالهم
In response, Yusor's mom told her to be kind to her neighbor,
وكرد فعل قالت أم يسر لها أن تكون لطيفة مع جارها،
that as he got to know them,
لأنه إذا عرفهم أكثر،
he'd see them for who they were.
سيرى حقيقتهم.
I guess we've all become so numb to the hatred
أعتقد أننا أصبحنا مخدرون تجاه الكراهية
that we couldn't have ever imagined it turning into fatal violence.
لدرجه أننا لم نكن نتصور أن يتحول الأمر إلى جريمة.
The man who murdered my brother turned himself in to the police
الرجل الذي قتل أخي سلم نفسه للشرطة
shortly after the murders,
بعد الجريمة بوقت قصير،
saying he killed three kids,
قائلاً أنه قتل ثلاثة أطفال،
execution-style,
بطريقة الإعدام،
over a parking dispute.
بسبب خلافٍ يخصّ موقف السيارات.
The police issued a premature public statement that morning,
قامت الشرطة بإعلان صحفي مبكر في ذلك الصباح،
echoing his claims without bothering to question it
لنشر اعترافه من غير التساؤل عنه
or further investigate.
أو حتى التحقيق فيه.
It turns out there was no parking dispute.
واتضح أنه لا يوجد خلاف بخصوص موقف السيارات.
There was no argument.
لم يكن هناك خلاف.
No violation.
ولا تعدٍّ.
But the damage was already done.
ولكن الضرر كان قد وقع فعلاً.
In a 24-hour media cycle,
في خلال 24 ساعة،
the words "parking dispute" had already become the go-to sound bite.
أصبحت "خلاف بخصوص مواقف السيارات" هي الكلمات السائدة.
I sit on my brother's bed and remember his words,
جلست على سرير أخي وتذكرت كلماته،
the words he gave me so freely and with so much love,
تلك الكلمات التي قالها لي بحرية وبحب كبير،
"I am who I am because of you."
"أنا ما أنا عليه بسببك"
That's what it takes for me to climb through my crippling grief
هذا ما ساعدني في اجتياز مرحلة الحزن
and speak out.
والتحدث.
I cannot let my family's deaths be diminished to a segment
لا يمكن أن أجعل أمر وفاة أفراد عائلتي يصغر
that is barely discussed on local news.
إلى أن يُناقش في الأخبار المحلية.
They were murdered by their neighbor because of their faith,
لقد تم قتلهم من قبل جارهم بسبب إيمانهم،
because of a piece of cloth they chose to don on their heads,
بسبب قطعة الثياب التي يختارونها لارتدائها على رؤوسهم،
because they were visibly Muslim.
لأنهم كانوا مسلمين واضحين.
Some of the rage I felt at the time
بعض الغضب الذي شعرت به في ذلك الوقت
was that if roles were reversed,
أنه في حال عُكست الأدوار،
and an Arab, Muslim or Muslim-appearing person
أنه إذا قام عربي أو مسلم أو شخص يبدو مسلمًا
had killed three white American college students execution-style,
بقتل ثلاثة طلاب أميركيين بيض بطريقة الإعدام،
in their home,
في منزلهم،
what would we have called it?
ماذا كنا سنسمي هذا الفعل؟
A terrorist attack.
هجومٌ إرهابي.
When white men commit acts of violence in the US,
عندما يقوم رجل أبيض بفعل عنيف في أميركا،
they're lone wolves,
يُسمى الأمر حالةً فردية،
mentally ill
أو مريض عقلي
or driven by a parking dispute.
أو خلاف بخصوص مواقف سيارات.
I know that I have to give my family voice,
أعلم أنني يجب أن أعطي عائلتي صوتًا،
and I do the only thing I know how:
وأقوم بفعل الشيء الوحيد الذي يمكنني فعله:
I send a Facebook message to everyone I know in media.
أن أرسل رسالة عبر الفيس بوك لكل شخص في وسائل الإعلام.
A couple of hours later,
بعد ساعتين،
in the midst of a chaotic house overflowing with friends and family,
في زحمة منزل ممتلئ بالأصدقاء والعائلة
our neighbor Neal comes over, sits down next to my parents
يأتي جارنا (نيل) إلينا ويجلس بجانب والدي،
and asks, "What can I do?"
ويسأل "ماذا يمكنني أن أفعل؟"
Neal had over two decades of experience in journalism,
نيل كان خبيرًا لأكثر من 20 سنة في الصحافة،
but he makes it clear that he's not there in his capacity as journalist,
ولكنه أوضح أنه ليس معنا كصحفي،
but as a neighbor who wants to help.
بل كجار يريد المساعدة.
I ask him what he thinks we should do,
سألته ما الذي يعتقد أنه علينا فعله،
given the bombardment of local media interview requests.
نظرًا للطلبات الكثيرة لإجراء المقابلات من قبل الإعلام المحلي.
He offers to set up a press conference at a local community center.
فاقترح أن يقوم بتجهيز مؤتمر صحفي في مركز المجتمع المحلي.
Even now I don't have the words to thank him.
حتى الآن، لا أملك كلماتٍ كافية لشكره.
"Just tell me when, and I'll have all the news channels present," he said.
قال "فقط أخبروني متى تريدون ذلك وسأجعل كل قنوات التلفزيون تأتي."
He did for us what we could not do for ourselves
فعل لنا ما عجزنا عن فعله لأنفسنا
in a moment of devastation.
في لحظه دمار.
I delivered the press statement,
قمت بالتحدث في مؤتمر صحفي
still wearing scrubs from the previous night.
وكنت لا أزال أرتدي ملابس الليلة السابقة.
And in under 24 hours from the murders,
وخلال أقل من 24 ساعة من حدوث الجريمة،
I'm on CNN being interviewed by Anderson Cooper.
كنت في قناة (سي إن إن) يقابلني أنديرسون كوبر.
The following day, major newspapers --
في اليوم التالي، قامت صحف كبيرة
including the New York Times, Chicago Tribune --
بما فيها نيويورك تايمز وشيكاغو تريبيون
published stories about Deah, Yusor and Razan,
بنشر قصص عن ضياء ويسر ورزان،
allowing us to reclaim the narrative
ليسمحوا لنا بالتحدث عن الموضوع
and call attention the mainstreaming of anti-Muslim hatred.
ولفت الانتباه للكره ضد المسلمين.
These days,
في هذه الأيام،
it feels like Islamophobia is a socially acceptable form of bigotry.
الخوف من المسلمين هو أحد أشكال التعصب المقبولة اجتماعيًا.
We just have to put up with it and smile.
يجب علينا فقط أن نتقبله ونبتسم.
The nasty stares,
النظرات البغيضة،
the palpable fear when boarding a plane,
شعور الناس بالخوف عندما نصعد طائرة ما،
the random pat downs at airports that happen 99 percent of the time.
التفتيش العشوائي في المطارات الذي يحدث 90% من المرات.
It doesn't stop there.
لا يتوقف الأمر عند ذلك،
We have politicians reaping political and financial gains off our backs.
فهنالك سياسيون يحصلون على مكاسب سياسة ومالية من خلالنا.
Here in the US,
هنا في الولايات المتحدة،
we have presidential candidates like Donald Trump,
لدينا مرشحون للرئاسة مثل دونالد ترامب،
casually calling to register American Muslims,
الذي يطلب تسجيل المسلمين الأميريكيين،
and ban Muslim immigrants and refugees from entering this country.
ومنع دخول المهاجرين واللاجئين المسلمين إلى أمريكا.
It is no coincidence that hate crimes rise
ليست مصادفة أن جرائم الكراهية تزداد
in parallel with election cycles.
في فترة الانتخابات.
Just a couple months ago, Khalid Jabara,
قبل شهرين فقط، قُتل (خالد جبارة)،
a Lebanese-American Christian,
وهو مسيحي لبناني أميركي،
was murdered in Oklahoma by his neighbor --
من قبل جاره في أوكلاهوما،
a man who called him a "filthy Arab."
وهو رجل كان يلقبه بالـ "العربي القذر."
This man was previously jailed for a mere 8 months,
ذلك الرجل تم سجنه لمدة ثماني أشهر،
after attempting run over Khalid's mother with his car.
لمحاولته دهس أم خالد بواسطة سيارته.
Chances are you haven't heard Khalid's story,
هناك احتمالٌ كبير أنكم لم تسمعوا قصة خالد،
because it didn't make it to national news.
لأنها لم تصل إلى الصحافة الوطنية.
The least we can do is call it what it is:
أقل ما يمكننا فعله هو أن نسميها:
a hate crime.
جريمة كراهية.
The least we can do is talk about it,
أقل ما يمكننا فعله هو التحدث عنها،
because violence and hatred doesn't just happen in a vacuum.
لأن الكراهية والعنف لا يأتيان من الفراغ.
Not long after coming back to work,
بعد عودتي للعمل بفترةٍ ليست طويلة،
I'm the senior on rounds in the hospital,
وأنا أقوم بجولات تفقد المرضى،
when one of my patients looks over at my colleague,
أخذت إحدى مرضاي بالنظر إلى زميلي،
gestures around her face and says, "San Bernardino,"
وأشارت إلى وجهها، وقالت، "سان بيرناردينو"،
referencing a recent terrorist attack.
مشيرةً إلى الجريمة التي حدثت مؤخرًا.
Here I am having just lost three family members to Islamophobia,
ها أنا اليوم قد فقدت ثلاثة من أفراد عائلتي بسبب الخوف من الإسلام،
having been a vocal advocate within my program
أقف لأدافع بصوتي من خلال برنامجي
on how to deal with such microaggressions,
حول كيفية التعامل مع مثل هذه الاعتداءات،
and yet --
وما زال الصمت سائدًا.
I was disheartened.
كنت بائسة،
Humiliated.
ومهانة.
Days later rounding on the same patient,
بعد أيام، وعند المرور على نفس المريضة،
she looks at me and says,
نظرت إليّ وقالت،
"Your people are killing people in Los Angeles."
"جماعتك يقتلون الناس في لوس أنجلوس"
I look around expectantly.
نظرت حولي بترقّب.
Again:
ومرةً أخرى:
silence.
لم يكن هنالك سوى الصمت.
I realize that yet again,
وأدركت ذلك ثانيةً،
I have to speak up for myself.
أنه يجب أن أتحدث عن نفسي.
I sit on her bed and gently ask her,
جلست على سريرها وقلت لها بهدوء
"Have I ever done anything but treat you with respect and kindness?
"هل فعلت أي شيء غير معالجتك باحترام ولطف؟
Have I done anything but give you compassionate care?"
هل فعلت أي شيء سوى الاهتمام بك بعطف؟"
She looks down and realizes what she said was wrong,
نظرت إلى الأسفل وقد أدركت أنها قالت أمرًا خاطئًا.
and in front of the entire team,
وأمام كامل الفريق الطبّي،
she apologizes and says,
اعتذرت وقالت،
"I should know better. I'm Mexican-American.
"يجب أن أكون أكثر إدركًا، أنني أمريكية من أصلٍ مكسيكي.
I receive this kind of treatment all the time."
وأمر بهذا النوع من المعاملة دومًا."
Many of us experience microaggressions on a daily basis.
كثيرٌ منا يواجهون اعتداءات صغيرة يوميًا.
Odds are you may have experienced it,
من المحتمل أنك واجهتها،
whether for your race,
سواء بسبب عرقك،
gender,
أو جنسك،
sexuality
أو طبيعتك الجنسية،
or religious beliefs.
أو اعتقاداتك الدينية.
We've all been in situations where we've witnessed something wrong
كلنا شهدنا مواقفًا رأينا فيها أمرًا خاطئًا
and didn't speak up.
ولم نتحدّث.
Maybe we weren't equipped with the tools to respond in the moment.
ربما لم نكن مجهزين بالأدوات اللازمة للاستجابة في تلك اللحظة.
Maybe we weren't even aware of our own implicit biases.
ربما لم نكن مدركين لتحيزاتنا الضمنية.
We can all agree that bigotry is unacceptable,
يمكننا جميعًا الاتفاق على أن العنصرية غير مقبولة،
but when we see it,
ولكن عندما نراها،
we're silent,
نبقى صامتين،
because it makes us uncomfortable.
لأنها تجعلنا غير مرتاحين.
But stepping right into that discomfort
ولكن أخذ خطوة نحو ذلك الأمر غير المريح
means you are also stepping into the ally zone.
يعني أنك أيضًا تأخذ خطوة نحو المساندة.
There may be over three million Muslims in America.
قد يوجد ما يفوق الثلاثة ملايين مسلم أمريكي في أميريكا
That's still just one percent of the total population.
وهذا لا يزال فقط واحد في المئة من التعداد السكاني.
Martin Luther King once said,
مارتن لوثر كنج قال،
"In the end,
"في النهاية
we will remember not the words of our enemies,
لن نتذكر كلمات عدونا
but the silence of our friends."
بل صمت أصدقائنا"
So what made my neighbor Neal's allyship so profound?
إذًا، ما الذي جعل مساندة جارنا نيل مهمة؟
A couple of things.
شيئان.
He was there as a neighbor who cared,
أنه كان جارًا مهتمًا،
but he was also bringing in his professional expertise and resources
لكنه كان أيضًا يقدم خبراته وموارده المهنية
when the moment called for it.
عندما تطلب الأمر ذلك منه.
Others have done the same.
فعل الآخرون المثل.
Larycia Hawkins drew on her platform
لاريشا هوكينز رسمت على منصتها
as the first tenured African-American professor at Wheaton College
كأول أستاذة أفريفية أميريكية في كلية ويتون
to wear a hijab in solidarity
سوف أرتدي الحجاب تضامنًا
with Muslim women who face discrimination every day.
مع النساء المسلمات لمواجهتهم التمييز كل يوم.
As a result, she lost her job.
وكنتيجة لفعلها خسرت وظيفتها.
Within a month,
خلال شهر
she joined the faculty at the University of Virginia,
انضمت إلى كلية في جامعة فيرجينا،
where she now works on pluralism, race, faith and culture.
وهي الآن تعمل على دراسة التعددية والعرق والإيمان والثقافة.
Reddit cofounder, Alexis Ohanian,
أليكس أوهانيان، أحد مؤسسي موقع ريديت،
demonstrated that not all active allyship needs to be so serious.
وضح أنه ليس من الضروري أن يكون جميع المساندين جادين جدًا.
He stepped up to support a 15-year-old Muslim girl's mission
ساعد بدعم فتاة مسلمة ذات 15 سنة في مهمتها
to introduce a hijab emoji.
لتقديم رمز تعبيري يرتدي حجابًا.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
It's a simple gesture,
إنه فعل بسيط،
but it has a significant subconscious impact
ولكن له تأثير غير واضح ومهم
on normalizing and humanizing Muslims,
في إظهار المسلمين بمظهر عادي وإنساني
including the community as a part of an "us"
وإدخالهم في المجتمع كجزء من "نحن"
instead of an "other."
بدلاً من "الآخر."
The editor in chief of Women's Running magazine
مدير تحرير مجلة المرأة
just put the first hijabi to ever be on the cover of a US fitness magazine.
وضع الحجاب لأول مرة في غلاف مجلة لياقة في أميريكا.
These are all very different examples
هذه مجموعة مختلفة من الأمثلة،
of people who drew upon their platforms and resources
لأناس استخدموا إمكانياتهم ومصادرهم،
in academia, tech and media,
في الناحية الأكاديمية والتكنولوجية والإعلام،
to actively express their allyship.
لكي يظهروا مساندتهم الفعالة.
What resources and expertise do you bring to the table?
ما هي المصادر والخبرات التي تقدمها أنت في هذا الأمر؟
Are you willing to step into your discomfort
هل تنوي الدخول في مساحة عدم الراحة
and speak up when you witness hateful bigotry?
والتحدث عندما تشهد الكراهية والعنصرية؟
Will you be Neal?
هل ستكون نيل؟
Many neighbors appeared in this story.
الكثير من الجيران ظهروا في هذه القصة
And you, in your respective communities, all have a Muslim neighbor,
وجميعكم لديه جيران مسلمين في حيّه السكنيّ،
colleague
زملاء،
or friend your child plays with at school.
أو أصدقاء لأبنائكم في المدرسة،
Reach out to them.
تواصلوا معهم.
Let them know you stand with them in solidarity.
أعلموهم أنكم تقفون معهم وتساندونهم
It may feel really small,
قد يبدو الأمر بسيطًا جدًا،
but I promise you it makes a difference.
ولكنني أؤكد لكم أنه يصنع فارقًا.
Nothing will ever bring back Deah, Yusor and Razan.
لن يعيد أي شيء ضياء ويسر ورزان.
But when we raise our collective voices,
ولكن في اللحظة التي نرفع فيها أصواتنا مجتمعة
that is when we stop the hate.
سوف نوقف الكراهية.
Thank you.
شكرًا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)